A Guide to the Beverly Willis Architectural Papers, 1954-1998
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
- Project Files, 1958-1998 (Map-case 1:1-15:2, Carton 1-49, Box 2-3)
  - Project 0660: Aliamanu Valley New Town, Honolulu, Hawaii, 1975 (Map-case 2:6, Carton 5, Box-folder 3:8-9, Map-case 1:26)
    - Project Papers (Carton 5)
      Includes contracts (in-house consultant and sub-contractor contracts), correspondence, site feasibility plan (CARLA), site conceptual design, and blank feasibility checklist
    - Project Report, 1975 (Box-folder 3:8-9)
  - Project 0661: City of Freemont Courthouse, 1975 (Carton 1)
    Project papers: special processing, EIR.
  - Project 0663: Green Point Terrace Apartments, 1975 (Carton 46)
  - Project 0664: Golden Gate Hospital, 1975 (Carton 46)
  - Project 0667: Navoto, 1975 (Carton 24)
  - Project 0669: School for Deaf Children (Special School EIR), 1975-1976 (Carton 6-7)
    Project papers; includes project information, reports, conceptual design, and loose drawings.
  - Project 0670: Green Valley, 1976 (Carton 24)
    Contract file and expenses.
  - Project 0671: Felson Townhouses, Fremont/High St. and Chapel Way, 1976 (Map-case 2:7, Carton 2:7)
    Master planning for multi-family housing; unbuilt.
    - Conceptual Design Drawing, 3
    - Slope Map #1, 1
    - Topography, 1
  - Project 0672: Harbor Bay, 1976 (Carton 46)
  - Project 0673: Pasadena City Hall, 1976 (Carton 46)
  - Project 0674: University Village Stores, Palo Alto, California, 1976 (Map-case 2:8, Carton 46)
    Provided design, construction drawings and supervision for retail store front.
    - Construction Drawing
  - Project 0675: Monterey/Poma Hicks, Monterey, California, 1976 (Map-case 2:9, Carton 9-10)
    - Areas of Common Slope, 1, computer generated
    - Drainage map, 1, computer-generated
    - Site Perspective, 1
    - Site Section, 3
    - Site Topography 2, 2, computer-generated
    - Slope Analysis, 2, computer-generated
    - Project Papers, 1975-1976 (Carton 9-10)
      General correspondence, clippings, meeting minutes, reference material, job notes, letters of transmittal, plans, background reports, studies, and environmental impact statement, site analyses, and development plans
      Not arranged beyond the series level.
  - Project 0676: IRS Computer Center Building Prototype, 1976-1979 (Map-case 2:10-3:8, Carton 11-12)
    Design and construction drawings for the Internal Revenue Service. Expandable prototypical computer center building to be adapted and built on nine campuses. Unbuilt.
    Extended Description: Designed by Willis in 1976 for the General Services Administration and the Internal Revenue Service (IRS), the project entailed the development of a prototypical computing center planned for construction on 9 regional complexes scattered throughout the United States. A totally flexible building, the hexagonal shape adapted easily to differing sites, the angular sides meshing with building configurations like a pinion and a wheel.
    Capable of accommodating 1 to 4 levels, Willis' design incorporated energy conservation techniques, task and user-friendly lighting and work stations, and flexible distribution systems researched and developed as a portion of the design scope. The open-air courtyard at the center of the building increased the amount of natural light and air available to the occupants and provided a natural compliment to the technologically-driven building.
    - Construction Drawings, 18 folders
    - Presentation Drawings, 1 folder
    - Project Papers, 1976-1979 (Carton 11-17)
      Includes specifications, loose drawings, sections, meeting minutes, job notes, correspondence, site adapt handbooks, sections, fee proposals, financial records, consultant contracts, submittal design developments, sections, incoming product information, architectural systems analysis and design criteria, acoustics, and details
      Not arranged.
  - Project 0677: Analysis of Computer Applications, 1976 (Carton 24)
    Planning of computer applications within office of construction.
  - Project 0678: Farm House, Boise Cascade, San Ramon, California, 1976 (Map-case 3:8)
    Master planning for farm house.
    - Circulations, 1
    - Common Slope Areas, 1
    - Land Use Distribution, 1
    - Parcel Map, 1
    - Slope Map (1), 1
    - Topography, 1, computer-generated
    - Unit Distribution Drawing, 1
  - Project 0679: Center Investment Site Investigation, Boise Cascade, San Ramon, California, 1976 (Map-case 11-14, Box 4, Carton 8)
    Master planning.
    - Grading Plan, 4
    - Plan Designation
    - Slope Analysis
    - After Grading Computer Contour
    - After Grading Cut/Fill, 3 pages
    - Area of Common Stability
    - Circulation Map
    - Cut/Fill Analysis, 3; 1 not used in final design
    - General Plan Designation, 2
    - General Drawing, 13
    - Geologic/Soils Map
    - Grading Plan, 4
    - Land Use Distribution, 2
    - Master Plan Designation
    - Physiography
    - Sections
    - Site Layout Map, 2 pages
    - Site Development Plan
    - Site/Utility Plan
    - Slope
    - Slope analysis
    - Soils Map
    - Unit Distribution Plan, 7
    - Project Papers (Carton 8)
  - Project 0681: 545 Mission Street, San Francisco, California, 1976 (Map-case 3:9-11)
    Design, construction drawings and supervision for office building renovation to include architectural offices on 4th floor of 5 story building.
    - Corporation Grant Deed, 1
    - Design Sketch, 7
    - Presentation Drawing
    - Seismic Engineering Drawings, 5
    - Maps
      - Topography
      - Street Noise
      - Major Buildings in Site Vicinity, 2
      - Existing Offices
      - Height Districts/Proposal
      - Parking
      - Transportation
      - Height Districts/Existing
  - Project 0682: Castro Street, San Francisco, California, 1976 (Carton 8)
    General Correspondence.
  - Project 0683: Bush Street, San Francisco, California, 1977 (Carton 8)
  - Project 0684: Mormon Church Site, 1977 (Carton 8)
  - Project 0685: T Corners, 1977 (Map-case 3:11, Carton 8)
    Master planning of multi-family housing and retail locations.
    - Construction Drawings, 1 set of 3 pages
    - General Correspondence (Carton 8)
  - Project 0686: Wolpert Ridge (Ponderosa Homes), Hayward, California, 1977 (Map-case 3:12, Carton 8)
    Master planning for multi-family housing development.
    - Preliminary Utility Layout, 1
    - Site Plans
      - Alternative Site Plan for Soda Property, 1
      - Site Plan, 2
    - Conceptual Design Drawing, 1
    - Grading Plan, 1
    - Presentation Documents
      - Area Map, 1
      - Aerial Photo, 1
      - Existing Topography, 1
      - Physiography, 1
      - Slope Map, 1
      - Site Plan, 1
    - Site Analysis, 1
    - Utilities Plan, 2
    - Project Papers (Carton 8)
      Includes CARLA materials, maps, an EIR draft, geologic report, feasibility study, and sewer study
  - Project 0687: Neary Residence, Oregon, 1977 (Map-case 3:13, Carton 46)
    Design.
    - Drawings
      - Conceptual Design, 28
      - Construction, 1 set of 17 pages
      - Presentation Drawings, 2
    - Design Sketches, 22
  - Project 0688: Galvin Residence, 1977 (Carton 46)
  - Project 0689: Menlo College Environmental Impact Report, 1977 (Carton 8)
  - Project 0690: Exxon Site, Richmond, California (Map-case 15:1, Carton 9)
    - Drawings
    - General Correspondence (Carton 9)
  - Project 0691: Silvarado Ranch, Almaden, California, 1977 (Map-case 3:15-4:2, Carton 9)
    Master planning for a subdivision.
    - Conceptual Designs
    - Maps
    - General Plan and Amendment
    - Unidentified Project Papers
  - Project 0692: Granite, 1977 (Map-case 4:3, Carton 20)
    - Site Plan
    - Project Papers (Carton 20)
      General correspondence, wastewater study, feasibility analysis, and traffic analysis
  - Project 0693: Vasco Property/Hayward, 1977 (Carton 46)
  - Project 0694: 7th and D Streets, Scotts Valley, California, 1977 (Map-case 4:4, Carton 18)
    Renovation of a government office building.
    - Conceptual Design Drawings, 3
    - Construction Drawing, 20 pages, not a complete set
    - Project Papers (Carton 18)
      General correspondence, final report
  - Project 0695: Far Eastern Traders, San Francisco, California, 1977 (Map-case 4:5, Carton 18)
    - Construction Drawings, 1 set of 32 pages
    - Presentation Documents, 1 set of 6 pages
    - Presentation Drawings, 10
    - Project Papers (Carton 18)
      General correspondence, red line set, specifications, fixture list, contractor contract, and interior design specifications
  - Project 0696: Veterans Home, 1977 (Map-case 16:1-2, Carton 19)
    Project Papers. Includes interior design requirements, product information, planning criteria for medical facilities, reports, job notes, and contracts.
  - Project 0697: VA Computer Facility, 1977 (Carton 8)
    Implementation Plan for VA OAC Computer Application.
  - Project 0698: Fremont Site Study, Fremont, California, 1977 (Map-case 4:6, Carton 20)
    Environmental impact report for multi-family housing development.
    - Parcel maps, 2
    - Site Plans, 2 pages
    - Project Papers (Carton 20)
  - Project 0699: Valley Project, 1977 (Carton 46)
  - Project 0701: Singleton Property, 1977 (Carton 20)
    Project Papers.
  - Project 0702: Cole Reed, Fremont, California, 1977 (Carton 20)
    Incoming correspondence, outgoing correspondence, memos, letters of transmittal, and job notes
  - Project 0703: Oak Meadow, Los Gatos, California, 1977 (Map-case 4:7, Carton 20)
    - Site Plan
    - Tree Study
    - Physiography
    - Parking Study
    - Schematic Utility Plan
    - item
    - Sections
    - Elevations
    - Project Papers (Carton 20)
      Incoming and outgoing correspondence, memos, meeting minutes, transmittals, job notes, a soil investigation report, and a medical facility appraisal report
  - Project 0704: Spinnaker Point (Carton 20)
  - Project 0705: Mission Palo Alto, San Mateo, California, 1977 (Map-case 4:8, Map-case 5:1, Carton 21)
    - Conceptual Design Drawing, 2
    - Design Sketches, 23
    - Building Plan, 1
    - Physiography, 1
    - Physiography for Redesign, 2
    - Presentation Documents, 1 set of 3 pages
    - Section, 1
    - Site Plan, 1
    - Site Plan for Redesign, 2
    - Project Papers (Carton 21)
      General correspondence, memos, meeting minutes, a letter of transmittal, and job notes
  - Project 0706: Evans Products, Portland, 1977 (Carton 46)
  - Project 0707: Haight and Fillmore, 1977 (Carton 21, 46)
    Unidentified project papers for a code analysis and feasibility study
  - Project 0708: Haight and Fillmore Apartments, San Francisco, California, 1977 (Map-case 5:2, Carton 46)
    Design; includes project papers for the Lippert/Haight St. Bar.
    - Building Plan
  - Project 0709: Palos Verdes Property, 1979 (Carton 46)
  - Project 0710: T.K. Hall, 1977 (Carton 21)
    Unidentified project papers
  - Project 0711: Inglenook Winery Wine Tasting Interior, United Vintners, Rutherford, California, 1978 (Map-case 5:2, Carton 21)
    Design for the interior of wine tasting and retail rooms, and displays.
    - Conceptual Design Drawing, 4
    - Presentation Drawing, 4
    - Project Papers (Carton 21)
      Unidentified materials, general correspondence, a feasibility study, miscellaneous materials, and general project information
  - Project 0712: Seamodal Transport Co., 1978 (Carton 46)
  - Project 0713: San Francisco Airport Energy Study, 1978 (Map-case 5:12, Carton 21)
    Bound volume, "Energy Conservation Design Criteria," and project papers, which include incoming and outgoing correspondence, general correspondence, meeting minutes, process planning, Q-1, step sheets, letter of transmittal, weekly action list, and contract information
  - Project 0714: Kordestani, 1978 (Carton 22)
    General correspondence and project papers
  - Project 0715: Lone Mountain College, San Francisco, California, 1978 (Map-case 5:3, Carton 22)
    Consulting.
    - Presentation Documents
      - Physiography
      - Schematic Site Plan
      - Site Plan
    - Project Papers (Carton 22)
      Two folders of general correspondence, a folder of project information, and one folder of unidentified materials
  - Project 0716: Margaret Heyward Playground Building, San Francisco, California, 1978 (Map-case 5:4, Carton 22)
    Project scope included design, construction drawings and supervision for a free standing building for small children. Building part of a large park with many different facilities.
    Extended Description: The Children's recreational Center at the Margaret Hayward Playground Park was designed and executed in 1982. Located in a modest-income neighborhood in San Francisco, California, the layer facade -- reminiscent of the segmented shell of an armadillo -- unfolds from the corner of the constrained site toward the outdoor play equipment.
    Willis designed the layers to act as theatrical backdrops, in an effort to encourage the children's imaginary performances and to allow for scalar shifts that accommodate both child and adult. A series of wide steps linking the playground and building entry create an impromptu thrust stage and child-sized seating area.
    Approximately 1,200 square feet of internal area accommodates the main recreational playroom, administrative offices and various support services.
    - Site Axonometric
    - Conceptual Design Drawing, 1
    - Construction Drawings
      One complete set for playground building at 19 pages, two pages (out of 12) for playground layout; one of retaining wall.
    - Design Sketch, 1
    - Schematic Plan, 3
    - Project Papers (Carton 22)
      Correspondence about the playground and programming
  - Project 0717: Lowe, Pacifica, California, 1978 (Carton 22)
    Two folders of general correspondence, a folder of project information, and a folder of unidentified materials
  - Project 0718: University California San Francisco, 1978 (Carton 46)
  - Project 0719: Soong Project, 1978 (Carton 46)
  - Project 0720: Ritchie & Ritchie, 1978 (Carton 46)
  - Project 0721: Haway-Haight Street, 1978 (Carton 22)
    General Correspondence
  - Project 0722: Alameda Creek, San Francisco, California, 1978 (Map-case 5:5, Carton 23)
    - Maps (annotated by Beverly Willis), 2
    - U.S. Army Engineer Corps Urban Study Drawings
    - Project Papers (Carton 23)
      Submittal materials, a production file, an unlabeled envelope, and an unlabeled binder
  - Project 0723: Seamodal Warehouse Building, San Francisco, California, 1978 (Map-case 5:6, Carton 23)
    - Conceptual Design Drawing (4 pages)
      Note: Includes 1 free-hand drawing of a plan, 1 free-hand drawing of a section, and 1 drawing for construction.
    - Construction Drawings, 4 (not a complete set)
    - Project Flowchart, 1
    - Specifications, 45
    - General Correspondence (Carton 23)
  - Project 0724: Fremont/Cole Reed Company, 1978 (Carton 23)
  - Project 0726: Ponderosa Homes, 1978 (Carton 46)
  - Project 0727: Master Planning, Vacaville, 1978 (Map-case 5:7, Carton 23)
    - Conceptual Design Drawing, 7
    - Presentation Documents, 11
      - Master Site Plan, 1
      - Planning Factors Drawing, 1
      - Density Study, 1
      - Traffic Study and Analysis, 2
      - Land Use Allocation-Circulation, 1
      - Transportation and Noise Elements, 1
      - Land Use, 1
      - General Plan Elements, 1
      - Circulation Alternatives, 1
      - Plan Alternative (general), 1
  - Project 0728: Thompson Associates, 1978 (Carton 46)
  - Project 0729: University of California San Francisco Nursing Building, 1978 (Carton 25)
    Project papers, including general correspondence, reference materials, a working drawing, details, a comparative feasibility study, and a conceptual estimate
  - Project 0732: Pollard and Ralston Consulting, Hawaii, 1979 (Map-case 5:8, Carton 23-24)
    - Conceptual Design Drawing, 7
    - Design Sketch, 2
    - Project Papers (Carton 23-24)
      EIRs, the Vacaville General Plan, feasibility analysis, reference materials, meeting minutes, job notes, and general correspondence
  - Project 0733: 2nd and Mission Street, San Francisco, California, 1979 (Carton 5)
    Project papers for an interior renovation.
  - Project 0734: Myers Residence, 1979 (Carton 5)
  - Project 0735: Pine Rock Apartments, Little Rock, Arkansas, 1979 (Map-case 5:9, Carton 46)
    Provided design, construction drawings and supervision for renovation of 48 condominiums.
    - Construction Drawings
  - Project 0736: Burnett Terrace Condominiums, 1979 (Carton 46)
  - Project 0737: Stevenson Project, 1979 (Carton 46)
  - Project 0738: McKinney Code Analysis, 1979 (Carton 5)
  - Project 0739: Zeimar Office, Burlingame, California, 1979 (Map-case 5:13)
    Consulting for a mixed-use development.
    - Design Sketch, 1
    - Map, 1
    - Photographs
      One aerial, one a printout of a photo used in a presentation document that illustrated shoreline development.
    - Presentation Documents, 1 incomplete set of 8 pages
    - Site Plan, 2 pages
    - General Correspondence (Carton 24)
  - Project 0741: Green Valley, 1982 (Carton 46)
  - Project 0743: Metcalf & Eddy, 1980 (Carton 24, 26-27)
    Energy report and analysis and miscellaneous project papers that include pamphlets, books, and computer printouts
  - Project 0744: Hodder Residence, 1980 (Carton 46)
  - Project 0745: Green Valley, Las Vegas, Nevada, 1980 (Map-case 5:10-11)
    Master plan for a new town of 100,000 people.
    Extended Description: By 1986, Green Valley -- an 8,400 acre planned community in the Nevada desert that would eventually house 100,000 residents -- had undergone sufficient development to support a small town- like commercial center. A 75 acre site adjacent to the Green Valley parkway was proposed for the Center. Willis executed a conceptual master plan for the site to accommodate phased development as future growth occurred. To provide a sense of community, Willis' plan proposed a full complement of retail, commercial, multi-family residential, entertainment, and recreational facilities.
    Given the physical discomfort entailed by the hot, arid climate, Willis incorporated environmental design strategies to minimize the unpleasant effects. Pedestrian arcades, towers with wind-catchers, moisturizing sprays, and landscaped "greenwalls" all served to reduce the effective daily temperature. As a focal point, Willis created a village green that fronted a four-plex cinema, an ice skating rink, and a variety of cafes and restaurants, providing a casual spill-over space for leisure activities.
    - Design Sketches
    - Design Submission, 2-page document
    - Maps of Area
      Mass-produced maps; include aerial and land use-maps
    - Presentation Documents
      - Films, 21
      - Development Sequences, 4
    - Section, 1
    - Site Plan, 1
    - Topography
  - Project 0748: San Francisco Wastewater Solids Study, 1982 (Carton 1982)
  - Project 0749: Fassler, 1980 (Carton 5)
    EIR, Project Papers.
  - Project 0751: Jesse St. Sub Station, San Francisco, California 1980 (Map-case 6:1, Carton 27)
    Study plan to determine feasibility to locate the Developer's Project Office in the existing Jesse Street Sub-station space, which was a former utility building.
    - Construction Drawing, 4 pages
    - Details, 3 pages
    - Design Sketch, 7 pages
    - Project Papers (Carton 27)
  - Project 0752: Yerba Buena Gardens, San Francisco, California, 1980-1981 (Map-case 6:2-9, 29)
    Created a master plan and conducted conceptual design for 24 acres in downtown San Francisco. Project part of a redevelopment project called Yerba Buena - joint venture of Beverly Willis Architects and Zeidler- Roberts Partnership, Toronto, Canada.
    Extended Description: Covering 24 acres--four city blocks--in downtown San Francisco, the Yerba Buena site was seen as a bridge that could extend the economic success of the financial and Union Street districts into the surrounding urban neighborhood ravaged by poorly conceived urban renewal projects. In 1980, the master plan put forth by the team of Beverly Willis Architects, Olympia & York, Ltd., the Marriott Corporation, and Zeidler-Roberts Partnership, Ltd. won an international competition for the site's development.
    Consisting of 1,250,000 square feet of office space, a 1,500-room hotel, 250,000 square feet of retail, 350 apartments, and an exhibition and performance art complex, the master plan created transitions in scale, use, texture, access that seamlessly rewove the urban fabric into an integrated whole. Ground level components were reduced in size creating a comfortable pedestrian street-scape that negated the presence of the 'super block' towers. A series of open spaces, sited for maximum sunlight and minimal wind, further reduced the scale and offered a variety of outdoor environments.
    - Axonometric Study
    - Photographs
    - Design Sketches, 18
      - Surrounding Areas, 14
    - Transparency of Site Plan
      - Design Sketches, 40
    - Shadow Diagrams
    - Site Plans
      One loose set; one complete set, including hotel lease, at 34 pages; and one transparency
    - Site Plans for the Asian Art Museum, 6
    - Conceptual Design Drawings, 59
    - Request for Qualifications, 1 booklet of 32 pages
    - Project Reports n.d., 1981, 2
    - Design Sketches and Studies, 110-page book
    - Project Notebook, 1980-1981
    - Watercolor (Map-case 14:2)
    - Presentation Documents
      One complete set reproduced photographically at 11 pages; one incomplete set of 7 pages, and presentation drawings (5 and proof set of presentation drawings of 9 pages).
    - Miscellaneous Project Papers (Carton 29)
      Job description, job notes, construction costs, correspondence, conceptual design sketches, invoices, and report.
  - Project 0753: San Francisco Ballet Building, 1981 (Map-case 7:1-8, Map-case 16:3-5, Carton 28)
    Project entailed building design, construction drawings and construction supervision for a new 4 story, 96 foot-high building in San Francisco's Civic Center.
    Extended Description: In the design of the building for the San Francisco Ballet Association, Willis was preoccupied with how the design could reflect the total fabric of a dancer's life. Located in the city's Civic Center, the site for the modest project of some 65,000 feet was surrounded by such monumentally-scaled buildings as the Opera House, Symphony Hall, the San Francisco Museum of Modern Art, and City Hall.
    To be compatible with the Civic Center's Neoclassical context, Willis used a tripartite horizontal ordering system derived from Renaissance principles on the facade. Breaking with classical tradition of symmetry, the entry was located on the corner, the curvilinear wall suggesting physical movement and offering a unique identity for the growing ballet company.
    As the dancers were required to spend six hours per day in the facility, the desire for natural light and outdoor air is reflected in the interior. In the large airy spaces visually accessible to the outdoors, Willis developed a mirror system to provide unbroken images of lifts and jumps, as well as a fluorescent lighting system free of the stroboscopic wavering that causes dizziness during practice. The building includes rehearsal, instructional, and administrative spaces along with food service, locker rooms, and lounges.
    - Building Plans, 1 set of 14 and 1 set of 65
    - Conceptual Design Drawing, 69 pages
    - Construction Drawing, 1 set of 116 pages
    - Design Sketch, 211 pages
    - Map, 1
    - Presentation Documents, Complete set of 12 pages
    - Presentation Drawing, 8
    - Section, 1
    - Site Plan, 4
    - Administrative layout, 1
    - Detail, 1
    - Elevation Concepts, 1
    - Elevations, 32
    - Facilities, 13 pages
    - General Drawings, 218
    - Massing Study, 1